or my family's life? Health concerns when there is no health system are also terrifying. I listened as many families had to sort through questions like, "My infant has a fever. What am I going to do?" "My sister, who is pregnant, is bleeding. What should I do? Who should I turn to?" "Where are the doctors, where are the nurses? If I could find one, are they trustworthy? How will I pay them? In what currency will I pay them?" "If I need medications, where will I find them? If I take those medications, are they actually counterfeits?" And on and on. So for life in these settings, the dominant theme, the dominant feature of life, is the incredible vulnerability that people have to manage day in and day out, because of the lack of social systems. And it actually turns out that this feature of life is incredibly difficult to explain and be understood by people who are living outside of it. I discovered this when I left Kosovo. I came back to Boston, I became a physician, I became a global public health policy researcher. I joined the Harvard Medical School and Brigham and Women's Hospital Division of Global Health. And I, as a researcher, really wanted to get started on this problem right away. I was like, "How do we reduce the crushing vulnerability of people living in these types of fragile settings? Is there any way we can start to think about how to protect and quickly recover the institutions that are critical to survival, like the health system?" And I have to say, I had amazing colleagues. But one interesting thing about it was, this was sort of an unusual question for them. They were kind of like, "Oh, if you work in war, doesn't that mean you work on refugee camps, and you work on documenting mass atrocities?" -- which is, by the way, very, very, very important. So it took me a while to explain why I was so passionate about this issue, until about six years ago. That's when this landmark study that looked at and described the public health consequences of war was published. They came to an incredible, provocative conclusion. These researchers concluded that the vast majority of death and disability from war happens after the cessation of conflict. So the most dangerous time to be a person living in a conflict-affected state is after the cessation of hostilities; it's after the peace deal has been signed. It's when that political solution has been achieved. That seems so puzzling, but of course it's not, because war kills people by robbing them of their clinics, of their hospitals, of their supply chains. Their doctors are targeted, are killed; they're on the run. And more invisible and yet more deadly is the destruction of the health governance institutions and their finances. So this is really not surprising at all to me. But what is surprising and somewhat dismaying, is how little impact this insight has had, in terms of how we think about human suffering and war. Let me give you a couple examples. Last year, you may remember, Ebola hit the West African country of Liberia. There was a lot of reporting about this group, Doctors Without Borders, sounding the alarm and calling for aid and assistance. But not a lot of that reporting answered the question: Why is Doctors Without Borders even in Liberia? Doctors Without Borders is an amazing organization, dedicated and designed to provide emergency care in war zones. Liberia's civil war had ended in 2003 -- that was 11 years before Ebola even struck. When Ebola struck Liberia, there were less than 50 doctors in the entire country of 4.5 million people. Doctors Without Borders is in Liberia because Liberia still doesn't really have a functioning health system, 11 years later. When the earthquake hit Haiti in 2010, the outpouring of international aid was phenomenal. But did you know that only two percent of that funding went to rebuild Haitian public institutions, including its health sector? From that perspective, Haitians continue to die from the earthquake even today. I recently met this gentleman. This is Dr. Nezar Ismet. He's the Minister of Health in the northern autonomous region of Iraq, in Kurdistan. Here he is announcing that in the last nine months, his country, his region, has increased from four million people to five million people. That's a 25 percent increase. Thousands of these new arrivals have experienced incredible trauma. His doctors are working 16-hour days without pay. His budget has not increased by 25 percent; it has decreased by 20 percent, as funding has flowed to security concerns and to short-term relief efforts. When his health sector fails -- and if history is any guide, it will -- how do you think that's going to influence the decision making of the five million people in his region as they think about whether they should flee that type of vulnerable living situation? So as you can see, this is a frustrating topic for me, and I really try to understand: Why the reluctance to protect and support indigenous health systems and security systems? I usually tier two concerns, two arguments. The first concern is about corruption, and the concern that people in these settings are corrupt and they are untrustworthy. And I will admit that I have met unsavory characters working in health sectors in these situations. But I will tell you that the opposite is absolutely true in every case I have worked on, from Afghanistan to Libya, to Kosovo, to Haiti, to Liberia -- I have met inspiring people, who, when the chips were down for their country, they risked everything to save their health institutions. The trick for the outsider who wants to help is identifying who those individuals are, and building a pathway for them to lead. That is exactly what happened in Afghanistan. One of the unsung and untold success stories of our nation-building effort in Afghanistan involved the World Bank in 2002 investing heavily in identifying, training and promoting Afghani health sector leaders. These health sector leaders have pulled off an incredible feat in Afghanistan. They have aggressively increased access to health care for the majority of the population. They are rapidly improving the health status of the Afghan population, which used to be the worst in the world. In fact, the Afghan Ministry of Health does things that I wish we would do in America. They use things like data to make policy. It's incredible. (Laughter) The other concern I hear a lot about is: "We just can't afford it, we just don't have the money. It's just unsustainable." I would submit to you that the current situation and the current system we have is the most expensive, inefficient system we could possibly conceive of. The current situation is that when governments like the US -- or, let's say, the collection of governments that make up the European Commission -- every year, they spend 15 billion dollars on just humanitarian and emergency and disaster relief worldwide. That's nothing about foreign aid, that's just disaster relief. Ninety-five percent of it goes to international relief agencies, that then have to import resources into these areas, and knit together some type of temporary health system, let's say, which they then dismantle and send away when they run out of money. So our job, it turns out, is very clear. We, as the global health community policy experts, our first job is to become experts in how to monitor the strengths and vulnerabilities of health systems in threatened situations. And that's when we see doctors fleeing, when we see health resources drying up, when we see institutions crumbling -- that's the emergency. That's when we need to sound the alarm and wave our arms. OK? Not now. Everyone can see that's an emergency, they don't need us to tell them that. Number two: places like where I work at Harvard need to take their cue from the World Bank experience in Afghanistan, and we need to -- and we will -- build robust platforms to support health sector leaders like these. These people risk their lives. I think we can match their courage with some support. Number three: we need to reach out and make new partnerships. At our global health center, we have launched a new initiative with NATO and other security policy makers to explore with them what they can do to protect health system institutions during deployments. We want them to see that protecting health systems and other critical social institutions is an integral part of their mission. It's not just about avoiding collateral damage; it's about winning the peace. But the most important partner we need to engage is you, the American public, and indeed, the world public. Because unless you understand the value of social institutions, like health systems in these fragile settings, you won't support efforts to save them. You won't click on that article that talks about "Hey, all those doctors are on the run in country X. I wonder what that means. I wonder what that means for that health system's ability to, let's say, detect influenza." "Hmm, it's probably not good." That's what I'd tell you. Up on the screen, I've put up my three favorite American institution defenders and builders. Over here is George C. Marshall, he was the guy that proposed the Marshall Plan to save all of Europe's economic institutions after World War II. And this Eleanor Roosevelt. Her work on human rights really serves as the foundation for all of our international human rights organizations. Then my big favorite is Ben Franklin, who did many things in terms of creating institutions, but was the midwife of our constitution. And I would say to you that these are folks who, when our country was threatened, or our world was threatened, they didn't retreat. They didn't talk about building walls. They talked about building institutions to protect human security, for their generation and also for ours. And I think our generation should do the same. Thank you. (Applause)
o la vida de mi familia? Los problemas de salud cuando no hay sistemas de salud también son aterradores. Solía escuchar a muchas familias hacerse preguntas del tipo, "Mi niño tiene fiebre. ¿Qué voy a hacer?" "Mi hermana, que está embarazada, está sangrando. ¿Qué debo hacer? ¿A quién debo acudir? "¿Dónde están los médicos y las enfermeras? Si encuentro uno, ¿cómo sé si son merecedores de confianza? ¿Cómo les voy a pagar? ¿Con qué moneda les voy a pagar?" "Si necesito medicamentos, ¿dónde los encuentro? ¿Y si tomo esos medicamentos y en realidad son equivocados? Y así sucesivamente. Entonces, al vivir en este contexto, el tema principal, la característica principal de la vida es la extrema vulnerabilidad en la que las personas viven día a día, por la falta de sistemas sociales. Y, de hecho, resulta que esta característica de la vida es sumamente difícil de explicar y de ser comprendida por aquellos que no la viven. Me di cuenta de esto cuando me fui de Kosovo. Volví a Boston, me convertí en médica, me convertí en investigadora de políticas sanitarias públicas mundiales. Ingresé en la Facultad de Medicina de Harvard y a la División Salud Mundial del Brigham and Women. Como investigadora, lo que realmente quería era resolver este problema. Pensaba, "¿Cómo reducir la vulnerabilidad devastadora de las personas que viven en este tipo de situaciones delicadas? ¿De qué manera podemos comenzar a pensar sobre cómo proteger y recuperar rápidamente a las instituciones que son esenciales para la subsistencia, como el sistema de salud?" Y debo decir que he tenido colegas increíbles. Pero lo que me resultó interesante fue que esta era una pregunta inusual para ellos. Decían, "Ah, si trabajas en la guerra, entonces significa que trabajas en campos de refugiados, y documentas atrocidades masivas, ¿no? - lo cual, de hecho, es muy pero muy importante. Me llevó un tiempo explicar por qué me apasionaba tanto este asunto, hasta hace casi seis años. Allí fue cuando este estudio histórico que atendía y describía las consecuencias de la guerra en cuanto a la salud pública fue publicado. Llegaron a una conclusión increíble y provocativa. Estos investigadores concluyeron que la mayoría de las muertes y discapacidades ocasionadas por la guerra suceden luego de finalizado el conflicto. Por eso, la época más peligrosa para vivir en un estado afectado por el conflicto es tras el cese de las hostilidades; es luego de la firma del tratado de paz. Es cuando se ha logrado dicha solución política. Eso suena muy desconcertante, pero definitivamente no lo es, porque las guerras matan a las personas al privarlas de sus clínicas, de sus hospitales, de sus sistemas de suministro. Los médicos se convierten en el blanco, son asesinados; huyen. Y más invisible, e incluso más mortal es la destrucción de las instituciones de gobernanza de salud y de sus finanzas. Entonces esto no me sorprende en lo más mínimo. Pero lo que sí me sorprende y me preocupa es el poco impacto que ha tenido esta introspección, en cuanto a cómo pensamos sobre el sufrimiento humano y la guerra. Déjenme darles un par de ejemplos. El año pasado, quizás se acuerden, el Ébola alcanzó a Liberia, país del África occidental. Hubo muchos reportajes sobre este grupo, Médicos Sin Fronteras, que daban la alarma y solicitaban ayuda. Pero casi ninguno de los reportajes contestaba la pregunta: ¿Por qué motivo está Médicos Sin Fronteras en Liberia? Médicos Sin Fronteras es una organización increíble, dedicada y diseñada para proporcionar cuidado de emergencia en zonas de guerra. La guerra civil en Liberia había terminado en el 2003, 11 años antes de que el Ébola afectara al país. Cuando el Ébola atacó en Liberia, habían menos de 50 médicos en todo el país de 4,5 millones de personas. Médicos Sin Fronteras se encuentra en Liberia porque Liberia aún no tiene un sistema de salud en funcionamiento, 11 años más tarde. Cuando el terremoto azotó Haití en 2010, la efusión de ayuda internacional fue impresionante. Pero, ¿sabían que solo el 2% de los fondos fueron para reconstruir las instituciones públicas de Hatí, incluso el sector sanitario? Desde ese punto de vista, los haitianos siguen muriendo a causa del terremoto incluso hoy en día. Hace poco conocí a este hombre. Este es el Dr. Nezar Ismet. Es el Ministro de Salud de la región autónoma del norte de Iraq, en Kurdistán. Está aquí para anunciar que en los últimos nueve meses, su país, su región, ha aumentado de cuatro millones de personas a cinco millones de personas. Eso es un aumento del 25 %. Miles de estos recién llegados han sufrido grandes traumas. Sus médicos trabajan 16 horas por día sin percibir sueldo. Su presupuesto no ha aumentado un 25 %: ha disminuido un 20 %, ya que los fondos se han invertido en temas de seguridad y ayuda a corto plazo. Cuando su sector sanitario falla, y como demuestra la historia, sucederá, ¿cómo creen que afectará la toma de decisiones de cinco millones de personas en su región porque piensan si deberían huir de estas condiciones de vida vulnerables? Como pueden ver, este es un tema frustrante para mí, y de verdad trato de entender: ¿Por qué la reticencia a proteger y apoyar sistemas de salud y seguridad autóctonas? Generalmente, tengo dos preocupaciones, dos argumentos. La primera preocupación es la corrupción, las personas en estos contextos son corruptas y poco fiables. Y admito que he conocido personajes desagradables trabajando en ámbitos de salud en estos contextos. Pero les diré que lo contrario es completamente cierto en todos los casos en los que trabajé, desde Afganistán a Libia, Kosovo, Haití, Liberia -- he conocido personas inspiradoras, quienes, cuando a su país le llegó la hora, arriesgaron todo para salvar las instituciones de salud. La clave para aquellos terceros que quieren ayudar está en identificar quiénes son esos individuos, y en construir un camino para que ellos lideren. Esto es exactamente lo que sucedió en Afganistán. Una de las historias de éxito olvidadas y nunca contadas de nuestro esfuerzo por construir una nación en Afganistán implicaba una gran inversión del Banco Mundial en 2002 para identificar, capacitar y promover a líderes afganos del sector sanitario. Estos líderes han llevado a cabo una gran hazaña en Afganistán. Han incrementado activamente el acceso a la asistencia médica para la mayoría de la población. Están mejorando el estatus sanitario de la población afgana, que solía ser el peor del mundo. De hecho, el Ministro de Salud afgano hace cosas que ojalá hiciéramos en EE. UU. Usan, por ejemplo, datos para elaborar políticas. Es increíble. (Risas) La otra preocupación que se oye mucho es "Simplemente no podemos pagarlo; no tenemos el dinero. Es insostenible". Les informo que la situación actual y el sistema que tenemos actualmente es el más caro e ineficiente que uno pueda imaginar. La situación actual es que cuando gobiernos como el de EE. UU. o, digamos, el conjunto de gobiernos que integran la Comisión Europea, gastan 15 mil millones de dólares cada año en asistencia humanitaria, de emergencia y en casos de catástrofe en todo el mundo. Eso no es asistencia externa, simplemente auxilio ante catástrofes. El 95 % se destina a agencias de asistencia internacional, que luego deben importar recursos a estas zonas, y desarrollar algún tipo de, digamos, sistema sanitario provisorio, que luego desmantelan cuando se quedan sin dinero. Por tanto, nuestro trabajo es evidente. Para nosotros, como expertos en políticas comunitarias de salud a nivel mundial, nuestro primer trabajo es volvernos expertos en cómo observar las fortalezas y debilidades de los sistemas de salud en situaciones de amenaza. Y ahí es cuando vemos a los médicos huir cuando vemos que los recursos se agotan, que las instituciones se desmoronan -- esa es la urgencia. Ahí es cuando debemos sonar la alarma y sacudir los brazos. ¿De acuerdo? Ahora no. Todos pueden ver que es urgente, no necesitan que les digamos. Número dos: los lugares como Harvard, donde trabajo, deben seguir el ejemplo de la experiencia del BM en Afganistán, y debemos -- y lo haremos -- construir bases sólidas para apoyar a los líderes de los sectores de salud. Estas personas arriesgan sus vidas. Creo que podemos emular su valor al brindar apoyo. Número tres: debemos establecer nuevas asociaciones de colaboración. En nuestro centro mundial de la salud, hemos lanzado una iniciativa con la OTAN y otros responsables de la seguridad para explorar qué pueden hacer ellos para proteger a las instituciones de salud durante su despliegue. Queremos que vean que proteger a los sistemas de salud y otras instituciones sociales esenciales es una parte fundamental de su misión. No se trata simplemente de evitar el daño colateral; se trata de alcanzar la paz. Pero los socios más importantes a los que debemos captar son Uds., el público estadounidense, y por supuesto el público mundial. Porque a menos que comprendan el valor de las instituciones sociales, como los sistemas de salud en contextos delicados, nunca apoyarán las iniciativas para salvarlos. Nunca harán clic en ese artículo que dice "Miren, en tal país todos esos médicos están huyendo. ¿Qué querrá decir? ¿Qué significará en cuanto a la habilidad de esos sistemas de salud para detectar la gripe?" "Mmm, probablemente no sea bueno". Eso es lo que les diría. En la pantalla pueden ver a mis tres defensores y creadores de instituciones favoritos. Aquí tenemos a George C. Marshall, él fue quien propuso el Plan Marshall para salvar, tras la 2ª Guerra Mundial, a las instituciones económicas europeas. Y esta es Eleanor Roosevelt. Su labor en materia de derechos humanos realmente sirve de cimiento para toda organización internacional de derechos humanos. Mi gran favorito es Ben Franklin, quien realizó mucho en cuanto a la creación de instituciones, pero dio a luz a nuestra constitución. Y les diré que estas personas quienes, cuando nuestro país se veía amenazado, o cuando el mundo se veía amenazado, no dieron marcha atrás. No hablaron de construir muros. Hablaron de crear instituciones para proteger la seguridad humana, para su generación y para la nuestra. Y creo que nuestra generación debería hacer lo mismo. Gracias. (Aplausos)